Today in the kitchen, we are going to do
a super luxury butter pecan ice cream...
I mean this one's going to be good,
so let's talk a bit more about it.
[Music] So butter pecan ice cream, it's got
a bit of a dark history. It originated in the
late 19th century up to Mid 20th century, born
from racism. It is believed that because vanilla
was exclusively available to white people, that
black folk back then turned to butter pecan as an
ice cream flavor as the way to get that luxury
that just wasn't available back then to them.
Thankfully the world has changed .....somewhat,
so let's talk about what butter pecan is.
Obviously it's pecan pieces they are toasted in
butter then there's a bit of a grey area as to
what the actual ice cream flavor is, some people
say it's just vanilla, a lot of people say it's
not just vanilla but they can't really determine
what it is. So I dug deeper into the history of
what it is and it turns out actually there's a few
different variations, one is just straight vanilla
ice cream, custard based with butter toasted
pecan halves or pieces in there. Then you've
got the start of the unknown variation, still
vanilla ice cream but there's something in it,
something about it that changes the flavor, boosts
this flavor. It's not butter extract. Then there's
another variation where we use different
types of sugar to change the flavor profile,
so as we're a science-based ice cream channel,
we're going to do a combination of all three. I'm
going to go down a route which produces not only
possibly the best vanilla ice cream you're ever
going to eat but also brings forward the flavor of
brown butter. Brown butter is when it goes through
the maillard reaction and you get these pieces
of toasted butter fat in there that creates a
flavor that you just can't achieve any other way.
So there's a couple of things that we're going
to need for this that you might not have in your
pantry and that is brown sugar, dark brown sugar.
Dark brown sugar is essentially just plain white
cane sugar with molasses and they add that back to
create this unique flavored sugar, we're going to
use this. It's been around for hundreds of years,
we're going to use this dark brown sugar if you
don't have dark brown sugar you can use white
sugar and molasses, combine the two but what
we get is this really rich caramelized sugar
kind of aroma and taste coming through it but
uh you know that's not the overall flavor cuz
we've got a lot of dairy going into this.
It's a custard base so we're going to be
using eggs and we're also going to be using
our housemade vanilla bean paste, you can use
vanilla extract, it's not as good as vanilla bean
paste but it will work in a pinch. We're looking
for that vanilla flavor vanilla bean paste gives
you, so much more of a complex vanilla flavor. So
what are we going to need for our ultimate butter
peacan ice cream you going to need 500g of milk
2% or full fat is fine, 544g of whipping cream
33%, 168g of dark brown sugar, 56g of dextrose
or corn syrup if you don't have dextrose, 67g of
skim milk powder, 10g of brown butter, 125g of egg
yolk and 25g of vanilla bean paste on top of that,
for the add-in we are going to need 150g of pecans
and 50g of salted butter. So now that we've got
all that down, let's get into the making of it.
What we're going to do is we're going to do our
pecans first because we're going to do these in
brown butter and we're going to take some of that
brown butter and put it aside because we're going
to use it in our ice cream base. Alright, so
I'm using a a really nice quality butter, it's
I think it was Safeway this so it's just grass
grass-fed butter, good quality butter please. So
what we're going to do is we're going to take 50g
of this butter and put it in our pan cut it up in
into little cubes we don't want one massive great
lump because we need this to melt evenly and that
is the process of doing brown butter, it is really
just about toasting the solids and here we go 50g
of butter and brown butter I think has origins in
France where it's called Beur Noisette, noisette
is hazelnut so ultimately it's called hazelnut
butter and that's because we get these toasted
flavors that come through that are reminiscent of
toasted hazelnuts. So with our butter in our pan
what we're going to do is just get this on a hob
and get it on a medium heat, we're going to keep
an eye on this because you can burn brown butter
quite easily. We're going to keep this going for
about 5 to 8 minutes what will happen is the
butter will foam up, that foam will start to
subside and gently we're going to cook that down
until we see and smell that toasted flavors come,
we'll see some little dark brown spots in our
butter. I'll show you in the a top down view so
I'm going to keep an eye on that so let's weigh
out our pecans. I know some of you will say oh
I say pecan's wrong... yeah well that's how I
say it, I'm English that's how English people
say pecan, I know in the US you say pecaaan
... say it how you want it's the same thing
So 150g there we go close enough now I don't want
huge pieces of pecan. Pecans are really oily nut
and they can come across as being quite stale
so just break them in half and that allows an
open end to the nut for that butter to go in and
Infuse that flavor into the nut itself what we're
going to do is we're going to just toast the peans
in another pan just for a couple of minutes bring
that flavor forward before we put it in our butter
so in that goes and on the hob just toast it for a
couple of minutes so our butter is heating up as
you can see it's starting to bubble we got it on
a medium heat so we're going to just keep swirling
this around we can see that that foam is starting
to happen on the top what will happen soon is
that butter will start to change transparency
our peans are coming up to temperature the smell
of the oil is coming out we got a lovely lovely
taste being infused into those now warming up
nicely you can keep that as high as it will go,
we're only doing it for a few minutes.
So our pecans are now nicely toasted, just at
that point where that smell is is developed lovely
bit of heat in those there we can now take those
off the heat and put them aside just put them in
a a small container like so we're going to need
to use this pan for our ice cream base what we can
do now is concentrate on our butter because we're
starting to get there you can see that foam the
bubbles have come up like this the initial white
foam has subsided the transparency is changing,
we're close now this is it, this is where we are,
we can turn the heat off, we don't want to burn
this perfect. What we're going to do is take
2 teaspoons of our brown butter and put it in a
small container, we're going to use that in our
ice cream but as you can see here look at those
solids that those solids toasted there that's
what's going to boost the flavor in our ice cream
but what we have here now is our butter we are
then going to add in our pecans and just stir
that around now in a hot toasted brown butter
and get those pecans absorbing that we can leave
that off the heat now to do its thing so we've
got our brown butter and our peans in here just
smell is incredible so we've got our 10g of our
browned butter here we're going to use it in our
ice cream so let's prepare our ice cream base.
Custard, I don't do custard often because I find
it semi- wasteful. It's basically impossible to
get egg yolks on their own over here in the stores
so you have to use whole eggs. You can achieve
this without egg yolks by using a stabilizer to
achieve a similar result but because of the flavor
that we are trying to get here in this brown
butter ice cream we want that egginess to come
through doesn't taste of egg but we we're we're
trying to deepen the flavor and that is something
that egg yolks can do in certain elements egg
yolks are excellent in vanilla ice cream so
that's what we're going to do do here we're going
to get our dairy and other ingredients in here
and get this going first thing we're going
to need 500g of milk cup measurements on the
screen, so it's enough to make two ninja
creamy Deluxe, two and 2/3 standard ninja
creamy and by the time we do overrun in our
churned which is what we're doing this in,
this will give us about 1.-6-1.7 L with our
overrun so a nice amount 544g of cream this is
33% whipping cream if you've only got 36% that is
fine, so 168g of our dark brown sugar ...Walmart.
Into that we're going to add our 10g of brown
butter, doesn't sound like a lot makes a huge
difference, we've got I showed you on the camera
got all these deepened toasted milk milk solids um
butter fat solids it's essentially the same
thing going in there that's really going to
boost that flavor for us this unknown flavor so
into that we're going to add our skim milk powder
and our dextrose 56g of our dextrose, skin milk
powder 67g and we've only got our egg yolks to
do now so what we can do is get this whisked
together and you'll find with that dark brown
sugar the color of this vanilla ice cream is
going to be like a light caramel color color
and that that is really really what changes
this you'll find that your solid your butter
solids will harden like this that is fine
because we're going to be putting this back
on the hob any minute now we need to do our egg
yolks and that is 125g of egg yolk here we go,
125g of egg yolks 1 2 3 4 5 6 eggs what we can
do is just add them all straight into our ice
cream base so making sure that that's completely
mixed in looks like a delicious caramel ice cream
but has no caramel flavor essentially just a
slight touch of it from our brown butter and our
dark brown sugar finally I'll put a link in the
description and a link up here where you can see
how to make this delicious vanilla bean paste
at home I one is that going to use that 25 to
30g of our vanilla bean paste we're going to make
this such a good vanilla ice cream that is our ice
cream base so let's get this on the hob and cook
it out whilst that's filming away there this video
was suggested by some of my patreon supporters
if you want me to make an ice cream and and you
want it guaranteed that I will make it head over
to patreon and sign up whatever you want a month
and you can then suggest some recipes and we will
talk about getting them on the channel uh the two
people that suggested this are longtime supporters
of the channel so great way of guaranteeing your
flavor to be sh on here so with our hob on a
medium height heat let's get this on and we're
just going to stand here and stir it until we get
up to about 70 to 75 C which is this in Fahrenheit
we don't need to go any higher than that we're not
using a stabilizer we've got our egg yolks in this
one so I'll come back War ups with there so there
we go nice and easy to achieve smell that's coming
through is incredible all we need to do now is
to chill this down it's um very very different
to a standard vanilla promise you this is one of
the best Vanilla Ice Creams you're going to eat so
with that in mind let's get this base chill down
in refrigerator we want to leave this overnight we
want to leave this for at least 12 hours for these
flavors to develop we got a lot of complex flavors
in here our brown butter our home made vanilla
bean paste dark brown sugar with molasses there's
a lot going on here let's give this time for these
flavors to develop all right 12 hours minimum 24
hours if you can one final thing we need to do is
to get our peans in our brown butter just stored
we're going to store these at room temperature
get all that brown butter in there with it cuz
we're waiting 24 hours for our ice cream base
that's going to allow the complex flavor of
that brown butter in those pecans to develop too
so leave this on the side now come back tomorrow
it's been days like 3 days yeah 3 days since I
started this recipe life takes over sometimes so
let's just quickly catch up for my sake more than
anyone else's cuz it's like 10 seconds since you
last on me anyway our delicious vanilla butter
pean bases here I'm going to do something a bit
special someone or a supporter of the channel
gave a suggestion which I'm going to do as well
as this so before we start I am going to pour off
some of that I'm not filling it right up so about
400 oh yeah it's about 400g in a standard
creamy tub on purpose so let's pop that in
the freezer this is going to be delicious
and let's get this in our [Music] machine
So whilst that is churning the obviously
because this has been sat for days,
the butter has hardened down at the bottom of
our pecans, you can see here the dark color is
all those caramelized solids from our burnt butter
they smell delicious but we need to separate that.
We need to melt this just enough to get those
liquid again so we can stir this up before adding
these into there we want to coat these again
before we put them in if you make these like now
at this stage then you won't need to do this but
sometimes you need to make things ahead so let's
melt this in the microwave for about 15 seconds.
So we're just going to stir these back together
get all those lovely caramelized solids in our
butter coating these pecans right we're we're
right at the end of our churn so let's get these
in I want that brown butter going in there as well
as that hits the ice cream it's going to freeze
into these gorgeous little nuggets of caramelized
brown butter this is just one of the things in
this recipe that sends this right over the edge
we want to get plenty of these peans in there save
a couple for decoration and we got all that yeah
let's get that good stuff in there don't don't
be afraid of doing something different honestly
I wish you could smell this this is this is
going to be good get this in the freezer dish
the rest up and I'll see you tomorrow following
day let's get some of this smells good dished up
[Music]
brown butter pecan ice cream,
beautiful scooping texture
amazing buttery pecans coming through they've
got that ever a slight caramelized flavor to
them with the brown butter in the ice cream really
boosts that flavor, we've got a caramelized note
as well because we used that dark brown sugar
with the Molasses already in there... honestly
this is something really special it's uh combined
with that Ultra Luxury vanilla bean paste that
we made on the channel a few months ago this
is an absolute winner. This is possibly the
best butter pecan ice cream you're ever going to
make it's got that unknown kind of flavor to it
that people can't determine what it is, but we
know what it is! incredible, one more spoonful
Now we haven't finished, there is a
supporter of the channel who suggested
something that they did at home
and I wanted to try it myself,
so earlier in the video I decanted some
of our mix into a ninja creami tub so
let's do that here we have our brown butter
pecan base, no pecans in there all right...
...that thing takes forever, check that out, nice
and what the suggestion was going to put a nice
divot down in the middle there we are going to
take a small pecan pie and we're going to just cut
that up and put that in our ninja creami tub take
a bite cover that over and let's put that back
on with our add-ins let's get that out I've got
another scoop it out there because I've just eaten
the first one because I need to do a thumbnail, so
let's just pop that in there there we go finally
all finished we have our more traditional brown
butter pecan ice cream which is a brown sugar
vanilla with brown butter custard base, Ultra
decadent base with our toasted in brown butter
peans we have the same base instead of the
pecans we've got pecan pie straight through
this ninja creami base, let's try this one.....
oh that's special..... I think I prefer this one!
They're both excellent there's little chewy bits
in there. The sugar base that goes into a pecan
pie it's kind of as obviously the ninja creami has
decimated that in the add-in spin, they've frozen
back up to create this chewy little nuggets
of deliciousness. Gary thank you, excellent
suggestion top, top recipe for the ninja creami
Ultra decadent butter pecan ice cream. Thanks
very much for watching, don't
forget to like and subscribe.
Next week we're going to be looking at how
to use a Sous Vide to cook ice cream bases,
so if you don't want to miss
that one, click that like button,
click that subscribe button
and I'll see you next time.